<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>PIPER: Resources for Teaching Physical Chemistry</title>
<link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/resources.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/resources.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>PIPER teaching resources for physical chemistry</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.33</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 06:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Practical Atmospheric Photochemical Kinetics for Undergraduate Teaching and Research</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/practical-atmospheric-photochemical-kinetics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/practical-atmospheric-photochemical-kinetics/practical.png" width="45%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>Including practical atmospheric chemistry in the undergraduate syllabus presents numerous challenges: most research grade equipment is too complex and expensive, and can require extensive safety training for students to use independently and efficiently. Herein we report an undergraduate analytical project that can be effectively performed in teaching laboratories equipped with standard UV-vis spectrometers, centered around an important application of photochemical kinetics in atmospheric research. Carbonyl compounds in cyclohexane can be considered to be “quasi-gas-phase”; therefore, measurements of their absorption spectra can provide useful information into the compound’s atmospheric photochemistry – a critically understudied aspect of atmospheric kinetics. We have delivered this course for two years and found that a project centered around collecting, processing, and understanding the atmospheric implications of these spectra is accessible to a range of student abilities and is an excellent tool for introducing the wider concepts and impacts of atmospheric chemistry.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<ol type="1">
<li>D’Souza Metcalf J., Winkless R., Smith S. C., Rickard A. R., Dillon T. J., ChemRxiv. 2025; <a href="https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-l5rgh-v2">doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-l5rgh-v2</a><br>
This content is a preprint and has not been peer-reviewed.</li>
</ol>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>kinetics</category>
  <category>environment</category>
  <category>spectroscopy</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/practical-atmospheric-photochemical-kinetics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/practical-atmospheric-photochemical-kinetics/practical.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="53" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Large Language Model (LLM) and Generative Pre-trained Transformer (GPT) References for Teachers</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/llms-gpt/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>References related to Large Language Model (LLM) and Generative Pre-trained Transformer (GPT) resources (e.g., ChatGPT) and their use in the chemistry classroom. Please send additions to ssinglet@coe.edu and I will include them in this list.</p>
<section id="classification-of-artificial-intelligence-applications-in-chemistry-from-automation-to-digital-scientific-thinking" class="level1">
<h1>Classification of artificial intelligence applications in chemistry: from automation to digital scientific thinking</h1>
<p>Ananikov VP. ChemRxiv. 2025; <a href="https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-fbk8w">doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-fbk8w</a> This content is a preprint and has not been peer-reviewed.</p>
<p>This article proposes a three-level classification of artificial intelligence (AI) application in chemical sciences, reflecting the increasing degree of technology involvement in scientific and production processes: from automation of routine tasks (the level of “AI Assistant”), to the creation of specialized analytical solutions for processing experimental data (the level of “AI Analyst”) and further to the prospect of intelligent systems capable of forming scientific hypotheses and designing substances and processes (the level of “AI Researcher”). This hierarchy enables systematic implementation of AI in practical chemistry, materials science, pharmaceuticals, catalytic technologies, environmental control, and other key areas. The first level contributes to increased efficiency in a wide range of tasks: in production, research and education, preparation of documentation, patent and market research, support of regulatory procedures, automated preparation of analytical data, as well as staff training and knowledge transfer within the organization. The second level provides in-depth data analysis, reduced R&amp;D timelines, and technology scaling. The third level opens up opportunities for breakthrough solutions, including autonomous design of new molecules, processes, and materials. The term “technology-as-participant” is introduced for the first time as a designation of a new form of interaction between humans and AI, in which the digital system becomes an integral part of the scientific process, not just a tool.</p>
</section>
<section id="an-investigation-of-change-in-prompting-strategies-in-a-semester-long-course-on-the-use-of-genai" class="level1">
<h1>An Investigation of Change in Prompting Strategies in a Semester-Long Course on the Use of GenAI</h1>
<p>Martin Sigot Sebastian Tassoti, J. Chem. Educ., 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01287">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01287</a></p>
<p>The increasing relevance of generative artificial intelligence in our everyday life prompts educational researchers to carefully assess science-learning experiences using this new technology. In this study, prompting strategies of preservice chemistry teachers were evaluated through the duration of a semester in several course settings. A course was developed that addresses the use of GenAI in contexts like problem solving in chemistry and teaching and learning chemistry and had the students individually work on a chemistry-related project. The course instructs the students in a specific prompting technique, the 5S prompting framework, to foster their prompting skills. During the semester and for a period after the semester, approximately 1600 prompts of students given to GenAI were collected via a custom-made interface that allowed researchers to see students’ prompts. The analysis of these conversations shows that students incorporated the prompting strategies they were taught in their conversations and interactions with GenAI during and after the semester. In this publication, the 5S prompting framework and its implementation in students’ prompting habits as well as implications for teaching about GenAI in chemistry-specific contexts are discussed.</p>
</section>
<section id="considering-the-ethics-of-large-machine-learning-models-in-the-chemical-sciences" class="level1">
<h1>Considering the Ethics of Large Machine Learning Models in the Chemical Sciences</h1>
<p>Spotte-Smith, Evan Walter Clark, ChemRxiv. 2025; <a href="https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-ct5k8-v2">doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-ct5k8-v2</a>. This content is a preprint and has not been peer-reviewed.</p>
<p>Foundation models, including large language models, vision-language models, and similar large-scale machine learning tools, are quickly becoming ubiquitous in society and in the professional world. Chemical practitioners are not immune to the appeal of foundation models, nor are they immune to the many risks and harms that these models introduce. In this work, I present the first analysis of foundation models using the combined lens of scientific ethics and chemical professional ethics. I find that general-purpose generative foundation models are in many ways incompatible with the moral practice of chemistry, though there are fewer ethical problems with chemistry-specific foundation models. My discussion concludes with an examination of how the harm associated with foundation models can be minimized and further poses a set of serious lingering questions for chemical practitioners and scientific ethicists.</p>
</section>
<section id="aichemistry-education-in-top-chinese-university-embedding-computational-thinking-into-curriculum" class="level1">
<h1>AI+Chemistry Education in Top Chinese University: Embedding Computational Thinking into Curriculum</h1>
<p>Wang R. ChemRxiv. 2025; <a href="https://doi.org/doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-8kh8t">doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-8kh8t</a> This content is a preprint and has not been peer-reviewed.</p>
<p>Integrating Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) into chemistry education requires shifting from treating AI as an opaque tool to cultivating students’ computational thinking—the ability to deconstruct algorithmic logic and apply it to solve chemical problems. Based on pre-curriculum investigation and analysis, this paper proposes an innovative interdisciplinary teaching framework that bridges AGI theory with chemistry education through computational thinking. By employing multidimensional strategies such as embodied cognition, metacognitive approaches, and phenomenon-based learning, we empower students to deconstruct the “black box” of AI algorithms and develop innovative domain-specific solutions. Pilot implementations demonstrate significant improvements in students’ understanding and application of AI for chemical problem-solving. Capitalizing on this advantage, the course has been included as a core required course in compulsory Chemical Engineering + AI undergaduation program of Tanwei College, Tsinghua University. This approach not only equips students with technical proficiency but also cultivates a generation of AI+Chemistry capable of co-designing AGI systems to address real-world challenges.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-missed-opportunity-for-no-code-chatbots-current-challenges-in-publicly-available-chemistry-gpts" class="level1">
<h1>A Missed Opportunity for No-Code Chatbots? Current Challenges in Publicly Available Chemistry GPTs</h1>
<p>Martin Sigot Sebastian Tassoti, J. Chem. Educ., 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01552">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01552</a></p>
<p>With the emergence of generative artificial intelligence (GenAI) and ChatGPT, individualization of learning pathways was discussed in the educational context. One way to achieve customization is the use of specialized versions of ChatGPT–so-called GPTs. Those GPTs are publicly available and used daily by thousands of people worldwide. In this work, we analyze the current market of chemistry-specialized GPTs in the OpenAI GPT ‘store’. We identify common shortcomings, such as unnecessary activation of features like DALL-E, overly positive use of terms like ‘expert’ or ‘teacher’ and the inclusion of copyrighted material. To highlight the urgency of well-designed GPTs in chemistry education, we analyze the most used chemistry-specific GPT in more detail to discuss further problems with GPTs. In summary, we advocate a collaborative effort within the chemistry education community to develop robust and publicly available GPTs. Future research might benefit from a focus on creating and refining these GPTs and exploring their impact on learning in both secondary and tertiary educational settings.</p>
</section>
<section id="investigating-the-uses-and-impacts-of-generative-artificial-intelligence-in-chemistry-education" class="level1">
<h1>Investigating the Uses and Impacts of Generative Artificial Intelligence in Chemistry Education</h1>
<p><a href="https://pubs.acs.org/page/jceda8/vi/genai2024?ref=vi_collection">Journal of Chemical Education Virtual Special Issue</a></p>
<p>Guest Editors: Elizabeth Yuriev, Monash University, Australia; Donald J. Wink, University of Illinois at Chicago, USA; Thomas A. Holme, Iowa State University, USA</p>
<p>Highlights the emerging applications of generative artificial intelligence (AI) in chemistry education. An accompanying editorial by the Guest Editor Team introduces the VSI.</p>
</section>
<section id="large-language-models-llms-as-graphing-tools-for-advanced-chemistry-education-and-research" class="level1">
<h1>Large Language Models (LLMs) as Graphing Tools for Advanced Chemistry Education and Research</h1>
<p>S. M. Supundrika Subasinghe, Simon G. GersibNeal P. Mankad, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01498">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01498</a></p>
<p>Large language models (LLMs) are positioned to transform how students interact with data in classroom and laboratory settings, both now and in the future. The integration of LLMs into chemical curricula, if done effectively, may improve student equity and learning outcomes and provide an alternative approach to data analysis alongside traditional methods. One of the key strengths of LLMs is their ability to efficiently summarize large data sets and transform them into understandable forms. Here we focus on use of LLMs to process quantitative data and make high-quality data plots without relying exclusively on spreadsheet skills. Specifically, we tested the ability of OpenAI’s ChatGPT to plot Walsh diagrams relevant to an ongoing laboratory experiment conducted in an undergraduate inorganic chemistry course.</p>
</section>
<section id="discussing-the-ethics-of-professional-ai-use-in-undergraduate-chemistry-courses" class="level1">
<h1>Discussing the Ethics of Professional AI Use in Undergraduate Chemistry Courses</h1>
<p>Emily F. Ruff, Jennifer M. O. Zemke, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01038">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01038</a></p>
<p>Teaching resources are needed to inform today’s undergraduate students about emerging uses of AI and help them think critically about corresponding ethical issues. We designed and piloted two exercises using articles from the popular press to introduce students to professional uses of AI in chemistry and related areas. Using student writing and follow-up assignments, we find that students are optimistic that AI will advance these fields but are also concerned that human labor and ideas should be protected. We close with suggestions for other instructors designing similar assignments.</p>
</section>
<section id="artificial-intelligence-in-chemistry-researchimplications-for-teaching-and-learning" class="level1">
<h1>Artificial Intelligence in Chemistry Research─Implications for Teaching and Learning</h1>
<p>Sandra Berber, Mathea Brückner, Nikolai Maurer, Johannes Huwer, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01033">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01033</a></p>
<p>Despite its growing relevance, the discussion of AI as a tool in research in (secondary) chemistry education remains limited. To address this gap, a review of AI applications in chemical and chemistry-related research was first carried out. Based on this review a workshop for pre- and in-service chemistry teachers was conducted to provide an initial overview of AI applications in scientific research. The workshop introduced key areas such as retrosynthesis, protein structure prediction, image processing, and autonomous laboratories, fostering awareness of AI’s role in scientific innovation. Participating secondary education science teachers reported an increased familiarity with AI applications and expressed intentions to incorporate these topics into their teaching.</p>
</section>
<section id="let-us-not-squander-the-affordances-of-llms-for-the-sake-of-expedience-using-retrieval-augmented-generative-ai-chatbots-to-support-and-evaluate-student-reasoning" class="level1">
<h1>Let Us Not Squander the Affordances of LLMs for the Sake of Expedience: Using Retrieval Augmented Generative AI Chatbots to Support and Evaluate Student Reasoning</h1>
<p>Melanie M. Cooper and Michael W. Klymkowsky, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00765">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00765</a></p>
<p>The use of large language model Generative AI (GenAI) systems by students and instructors is increasing rapidly, and there is little choice but to adapt to this new situation. Many, but not all, students are using GenAI for homework and assignments, which means that we need to provide equitable access for all students to AI systems that can support and enhance their learning. At the same time, we need to think carefully about just what we want teaching and learning to look like as GenAI systems become readily available. Here we propose that “business as usual” is not a responsible option. Although chatbots can readily answer questions, produce summaries of content, and make the process of education more efficient, there is scant evidence that such time saving is effective, and indeed, it is important that we not allow the use of GenAI systems to circumvent or undermine the learning process. The availability of so-called Retrieval Augmented Generative (RAG) AI systems allows us to expand what we expect students to know and do, by 1) supporting instructors in the design of more complex tasks (that can, for example, elicit evidence of three-dimensional learning (3DL)), 2) supporting students as they reason through such scaffolded tasks, and 3) by evaluating student responses, individually and in aggregate. We present examples of each of these affordances with the associated training materials and bot personas, along with caveats about their use.</p>
</section>
<section id="using-generative-ai-systems-for-critical-thinking-engagement-in-an-advanced-chemistry-course-a-case-study" class="level1">
<h1>Using Generative AI Systems for Critical Thinking Engagement in an Advanced Chemistry Course: A Case Study</h1>
<p>Pence, et. al., J. Chem. Educ. 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00242">doi: 10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00242</a></p>
<p>A series of critical thinking assignments was created for students in an advanced chemistry course to interact with and evaluate generative AI (GenAI) systems. Students explored GenAI’s facility with producing summaries of C&amp;EN articles, analyzing titration data, and closely reading literature articles. For each assignment, the students evaluated the output using a critical thinking exercise and presented their results using written reports. The students found GenAI to be effective at summarizing news articles, although it demonstrated inaccuracies in mathematical calculations and produced mixed results in answering technical questions based on specific literature articles. The assignments provided valuable practice for students’ critical thinking skills.</p>
</section>
<section id="enhancing-ai-responses-in-chemistry-integrating-text-generation-image-creation-and-image-interpretation-through-different-levels-of-prompts" class="level1">
<h1>Enhancing AI Responses in Chemistry: Integrating Text Generation, Image Creation, and Image Interpretation through Different Levels of Prompts</h1>
<p>Wilton J. D. Nascimento Júnior, Carla Morais, Gildo Girotto Júnior, <em>J. Chem. Ed.</em>, 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00230">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00230</a></p>
<p>Generative Artificial Intelligence technologies can potentially transform education, benefiting teachers and students. This study evaluated various GAIs, including ChatGPT 3.5, ChatGPT 4.0, Google Bard, Bing Chat, Adobe Firefly, Leonardo.AI, and DALL-E, focusing on textual and imagery content. Utilizing initial, intermediate, and advanced prompts, we aim to simulate GAI responses tailored to users with varying levels of knowledge. We aim to investigate the possibilities of integrating content from Chemistry Teaching. The systems presented responses appropriate to the scientific consensus for textual generation, but they revealed alternative chemical content conceptions. In terms of the interpretation of chemical system representations, only ChatGPT 4.0 accurately identified the content in all of the images. In terms of image production, even with more advanced prompts and subprompts, Generative Artificial Intelligence still presents difficulties in content production. The use of prompts involving the Python language promoted an improvement in the images produced. In general, we can consider content production as support for chemistry teaching, but only with more advanced prompts do the answers tend to present fewer errors. The importance of previously understanding chemistry concepts and systems’ functioning is noted.</p>
</section>
<section id="chatgpt-as-an-instructors-assistant-for-generating-and-scoring-exams" class="level1">
<h1>ChatGPT as an Instructor’s Assistant for Generating and Scoring Exams</h1>
<p>Alberto A. Fernández, Margarita López-Torres, Jesús J. Fernández, Digna Vázquez-García J. Chem. Educ. 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00231" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00231</a>, CC-BY</p>
<p>This study assessed ChatGPT’s proficiency in responding to questions from University Entrance Exams typically administered to senior secondary students. Our findings indicate that ChatGPT version 4.0 consistently outperformed students, achieving higher average scores across exams from the past four years. However, it still committed errors in about 20% of its responses. Despite this, ChatGPT 4.0 demonstrated a robust capability to comprehend and produce natural language within a chemical context. Consequently, by applying diverse prompt engineering techniques, this AI was able to create short-answer questions and numerical problems that closely mimic the format and conceptual content of University Entrance Exams. We also confirmed that ChatGPT 4.0 could grade exams, showing a significant correlation with scores given by human evaluators but lower than that among human graders. This discrepancy and other practical considerations limit its application in grading exams.</p>
</section>
<section id="exploring-the-concept-of-valence-and-the-nature-of-science-via-generative-artificial-intelligence-and-general-chemistry-textbooks" class="level1">
<h1>Exploring the Concept of Valence and the Nature of Science via Generative Artificial Intelligence and General Chemistry Textbooks</h1>
<p>Rebecca M. Jones, Eva-Maria Rudler, Conner Preston, J. Chem. Educ., 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00271" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00271</a></p>
<p>This paper explores historical and modern perspectives of the concept of valence in the context of collegiate general chemistry and draws comparisons to responses from generative artificial intelligence (genAI) tools such as ChatGPT. A fundamental concept in chemistry, valence in the early and mid-20th century was primarily defined as the “combining capacity” of atoms. Twenty-first century textbooks do not include this historical definition but rather use valence as an adjective to modify other nouns, e.g., valence electron or valence orbital. To explore these different perspectives in other information sources that could be used by students, we used a systematic series of prompts about valence to analyze the responses from ChatGPT, Bard, Liner, and ChatSonic from September and December 2023. Our findings show the historical definition is very common in responses to prompts which use valence or valency as a noun but less common when prompts include valence as an adjective. Regarding this concept, the state-of-the-art genAI tools are more consistent with textbooks from the 1950s than modern collegiate general chemistry textbooks. These findings present an opportunity for chemistry educators to observe and discuss with students the nature of science and how our understanding of chemistry changes. Including implications for educators, we present an example activity that may be deployed in general chemistry classes.</p>
</section>
<section id="student-perceptions-of-artificial-intelligence-utility-in-the-introductory-chemistry-classroom" class="level1">
<h1>Student Perceptions of Artificial Intelligence Utility in the Introductory Chemistry Classroom</h1>
<p>Mendez, James D., J. Chem. Educ., 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00075" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00075</a></p>
<p>This study investigates student perceptions of generative artificial intelligence (AI) in an introductory chemistry course. Students engaged with AI chatbots of their choice to correct missed exam questions, revealing overall positive attitudes toward their usefulness. Despite this positive perception, the study shows a disconnect between the overall media portrayal of AI in academia and how actual students use it. Only a small number of students had used AI before this activity. This study highlights the need for training on responsible AI use to address ongoing ethical concerns over the misuse of these systems and to get ahead of future issues.</p>
</section>
<section id="large-language-models-are-catalyzing-chemistry-education" class="level1">
<h1>Large Language Models are Catalyzing Chemistry Education</h1>
<p>Du Y, Duan C, Bran A, Sotnikova A, Qu Y, Kulik H, et al., ChemRxiv. 2024; <a href="https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2024-h722v">doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2024-h722v</a></p>
<p>Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated outstanding capabilities in general problem-solving and been shown to improve productivity in certain domains. Thanks to their flexibility, recent work has leveraged them for diverse scientific applications, ranging from predictive modeling, scientific Q&amp;A, and even as autonomous agents towards automation in chemistry. The democratization of high-quality chemistry education faces several challenges, including heterogeneity among sub-fields, limited access to personalized guidance, and an uneven distribution of resources. Additionally, hands-on laboratory experiments, a crucial component of chemistry education, are difficult to scale due to inherent safety risks that necessitate close supervision. We propose that LLMs can help overcome these obstacles by providing scalable solutions that tailor educational content to individual needs, enhancing the overall learning experience. In this perspective, we discuss how LLMs can catalyze chemistry education across multiple dimensions, from preparing and delivering lectures and tackling guidance in both wet lab and computational experiments, to re-thinking evaluation methodologies in the classroom. We also discuss some potential risks of this technology, such as the possibility of generating inaccurate or biased content, and emphasize the need for further development to ensure the successful integration of LLMs in the chemistry classroom.</p>
</section>
<section id="using-chatgpt-to-support-lesson-planning-for-the-historical-experiments-of-thomson-millikan-and-rutherford" class="level1">
<h1>Using ChatGPT to Support Lesson Planning for the Historical Experiments of Thomson, Millikan, and Rutherford</h1>
<p>Ted M. Clark, Matthew Fhaner, Matthew Stoltzfus, and Matt Scott Queen, J. Chem. Ed., 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00200">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00200</a></p>
<p>Four General Chemistry instructors investigated the use of ChatGPT-4 to improve their lessons plans for the historical experiments of Thomson, Millikan, and Rutherford. The instructors varied in their prior knowledge for these experiments and their initial lessons addressed somewhat different learning objectives. This led to different conversations with the chatbot as the instructors used the resource in different ways and discussed topics they each found relevant. The output from ChatGPT-4 was robust and each instructor identified ways it could be used to improve their instruction. The chatbot was able to accomplish instructional tasks these instructors found useful, such as outlining a lesson plan, recommending resources, discussing instructional strategies, describing calculations, offering explanations for different levels of leaners, and generating assessments. A limitation was its ability create images or visual aids the instructors found useful. Overall, these instructors found the chatbot could support, but not replace, an instructor in a course like General Chemistry.</p>
</section>
<section id="students-experience-of-a-chatgpt-enabled-final-exam-in-a-non-majors-chemistry-course" class="level1">
<h1>Students’ Experience of a ChatGPT Enabled Final Exam in a Non-Majors Chemistry Course</h1>
<p>Morgan J. Clark, Micke Reynders, and Thomas A. Holme, Journal of Chemical Education, 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00161">DOI: 10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00161</a></p>
<p>In the field of education, ChatGPT has become a topic of debate for its usefulness as a learning tool. This article focuses on non-science majors’ (n = 29) perceptions of a ChatGPT enabled final exam, where, prior to the exam, students wrote papers on science and sustainability and, during the final exam, students were asked to compare their paper to one produced on the same topic by ChatGPT. Thus, the underlying chemistry, its broader impacts, and connection to sustainability and writing styles were compared. Students’ perceptions were analyzed through a developed coding framework that enabled the visualization of emerging themes. The most common themes revealed that students believed the ChatGPT essay did not read as “human-like”, used more intricate words, and often did not include enough science to support its arguments. Students also noted that their essays provided more chemistry details and were easier to read as they focused on connecting chemistry concepts to their essay topic as well as sustainable policies and practices. Students were impressed, however, by ChatGPT’s ability to discuss various sustainability solutions, policies, and practices. The final exam inspired self-reflection for the students to improve not only their writing but also their analysis of sustainability responses. Overall, students rated the comparative activity as a final exam to be favorable and remarked on the importance of analyzing AI generated work for the future of learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-chatgpt-enhance-chemistry-laboratory-teaching-using-prompt-engineering-to-enable-ai-in-generating-laboratory-activities" class="level1">
<h1>Can ChatGPT Enhance Chemistry Laboratory Teaching? Using Prompt Engineering to Enable AI in Generating Laboratory Activities</h1>
<p>José Luís Araújo and Isabel Saúde, Journal of Chemical Education, 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00745" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00745</a></p>
<p>The rapid evolution of Artificial Intelligence (AI) is profoundly shaping our society. Among various AI tools, ChatGPT stands out for its user-friendly nature and wide accessibility to the public. However, despite their countless potential benefits, these tools also face significant challenges, especially in sensitive areas like Education. In this publication, we conduct a prompt engineering essay with ChatGPT to understand the potential and challenges of this tool in designing new, high-quality chemistry laboratory activities. We aimed to assess its performance in proposing scientifically and pedagogically suitable protocols for chemistry laboratory activities based on the 11th-grade Portuguese curriculum. The initial exploratory essay was conducted to fine-tune the prompt, followed by the analysis of proposals for the five mandatory laboratory activities in this subject. ChatGPT demonstrates the ability to interpret and reproduce the specialized symbolic language of chemistry, effectively conceptualizing problems and laboratory activities in a clear and understandable manner for a broader audience (i.e., chemistry students). However, it is crucial to highlight the scientific-pedagogical limitations concerning the accuracy and appropriateness of the proposed laboratory activities, particularly in terms of safety and sustainability. Therefore, the use of AI in education should be approached critically and reflectively. While AI holds immense potential to transform the dynamics of teaching and learning, the role and expertise of the Chemistry teacher remain of the utmost importance to ensure the scientific and pedagogical quality of Chemistry classes.</p>
</section>
<section id="comment-on-comparing-the-performance-of-college-chemistry-students-with-chatgpt-for-calculations-involving-acids-and-bases" class="level1">
<h1>Comment on “Comparing the Performance of College Chemistry Students with ChatGPT for Calculations Involving Acids and Bases”</h1>
<p>Joshua Schrier, Journal of Chemical Education, 2024, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00058">10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00058</a></p>
<p>In a recent paper in this Journal ( J. Chem. Educ. 2023, 100, 3934−3944), Clark et al.&nbsp;evaluated the performance of the GPT-3.5 large language model (LLM) on ten undergraduate pH calculation problems. They reported that GPT-3.5 gave especially poor results for salt and titration problems, returning the correct results only 10% and 0% of the time, respectively, and that, despite a correct application of heuristics, the LLM made mathematical errors and used flawed strategies. However, these problems are partially mitigated using the more advanced GPT-4 model and entirely corrected using simple prompting and calculator tool use patterns demonstrated herein.</p>
</section>
<section id="leveraging-chatgpt-for-enhancing-critical-thinking-skills" class="level1">
<h1>Leveraging ChatGPT for Enhancing Critical Thinking Skills</h1>
<p>Ying Guo, Daniel Lee <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00505">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00505</a></p>
<p>This article presents a study conducted at Georgia Gwinnett College (GGC) to explore the use of ChatGPT, a large language model, for fostering critical thinking skills in higher education. The study implemented a ChatGPT-based activity in introductory chemistry courses, where students engaged with ChatGPT in three stages: account setup and orientation, essay creation, and output revision and validation. The results showed significant improvements in students’ confidence to ask insightful questions, analyze information, and comprehend complex concepts. Students reported that ChatGPT provided diverse perspectives and challenged their current ways of thinking. They also expressed an increased utilization of ChatGPT to enhance critical thinking skills and a willingness to recommend it to others. However, challenges included low-quality student comments and difficulties in validating information sources. The study highlights the importance of comprehensive training for educators and access to reliable resources. Future research should focus on training educators in integrating ChatGPT effectively and ensuring student awareness of privacy and security considerations. In conclusion, this study provides valuable insights for leveraging AI technologies like ChatGPT to foster critical thinking skills in higher education.</p>
</section>
<section id="an-analysis-of-ai-generated-laboratory-reports-across-the-chemistry-curriculum-and-student-perceptions-of-chatgpt" class="level1">
<h1>An Analysis of AI-Generated Laboratory Reports across the Chemistry Curriculum and Student Perceptions of ChatGPT</h1>
<p>Joseph K. West, Jeanne L. Franz, Sara M. Hein, Hannah R. Leverentz-Culp, Jonathon F. Mauser, Emily F. Ruff, and Jennifer M. Zemke <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00581">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00581</a></p>
<p>AI technologies are rapidly pervading many areas of our world. AI-driven text generators such as ChatGPT are at the forefront of this due to their simplicity and accessibility. Their influence on higher education is already being observed, and perceptions among faculty and students vary widely. We have undertaken a cross-curriculum study of ChatGPT’s ability to generate laboratory reports. AI-generated reports from general, organic, analytical, physical, inorganic, and biochemistry courses were graded as if they were student reports and analyzed for grade distributions and common strengths and weaknesses. To further gauge ChatGPT’s current impact, we surveyed all students in our Spring 2023 laboratory courses regarding their awareness and use of ChatGPT. We have also laid out suggestions, guidance, and considerations for instructors who wish to prohibit ChatGPT use by their students as well as for those who wish to begin incorporating this new, powerful tool into their teaching.</p>
</section>
<section id="using-generative-artificial-intelligence-in-chemistry-education-research-prioritizing-ethical-use-and-accessibility" class="level1">
<h1>Using generative artificial intelligence in chemistry education research: prioritizing ethical use and accessibility</h1>
<p>Deng JM, Lalani Z, McDermaid LA, Szozda AR, <a href="https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2023-24zfl" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2023-24zfl</a> (unreviewed preprint)</p>
<p>Generative artificial intelligence (GenAI) has the potential to drastically alter how we teach and conduct research in chemistry education. There have been many reports on the potential uses, limitations, and considerations for GenAI tools in teaching and learning, but there have been fewer discussions of how such tools could be leveraged in educational research, including in chemistry education research. GenAI tools can be used to facilitate and support researchers in every stage of traditional educational research projects (e.g.&nbsp;conducting literature reviews, designing research questions and methods, communicating results). However, these tools also have existing limitations that researchers must be aware of prior to and during use. In this research commentary, we share insights on how chemistry education researchers can use GenAI tools in their work ethically. We also share how GenAI tools can be leveraged to improve accessibility and equity in research.</p>
</section>
<section id="chatgpt-needs-a-chemistry-tutor-too" class="level1">
<h1>ChatGPT Needs a Chemistry Tutor, Too</h1>
<p>Alfredo J. Leon and Dinesh Vidhani, Journal of Chemical Education, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00288" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00288</a></p>
<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) technology has the potential to revolutionize the education sector. This study sought to determine the efficacy of ChatGPT to correctly answer questions a learner would use and to elucidate how the AI was processing potential prompts. Our goal was to evaluate the role of prompt formats, response consistency, and reliability of ChatGPT responses. Analyzing prompt format, we see that the data do not demonstrate a statistically significant difference between multiple-choice and free-response questions. Neither format achieved scores higher than 37%, and testing at different locations did not improve scores. Interestingly, ChatGPT’s free version provides accurate responses to discipline-specific questions that contain information from unrelated topics as distractors, improving its accuracy over the free-response questions. It is important to consider, while ChatGPT can identify the correct answer within a given context, it may not be able to determine if the answer it selects is correct computationally or through analysis. The results of this study can guide future AI and ChatGPT training practices and implementations to ensure they are used to their fullest potential.</p>
</section>
<section id="scibench-evaluating-college-level-scientific-problem-solving-abilities-of-large-language-models" class="level1">
<h1>SciBench: Evaluating College-Level Scientific Problem-Solving Abilities of Large Language Models</h1>
<p>Xiaoxuan Wang, et al, arXiv Computer Science, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10635" class="uri">https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10635</a></p>
<p>Abstract: Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated notable progress on many mathematical benchmarks. However, most of these benchmarks only feature problems grounded in junior and senior high school subjects, contain only multiple-choice questions, and are confined to a limited scope of elementary arithmetic operations. To address these issues, this paper introduces an expansive benchmark suite SciBench that aims to systematically examine the reasoning capabilities required for complex scientific problem solving. SciBench contains two carefully curated datasets: an open set featuring a range of collegiate-level scientific problems drawn from mathematics, chemistry, and physics textbooks, and a closed set comprising problems from undergraduate-level exams in computer science and mathematics. Based on the two datasets, we conduct an in-depth benchmark study of two representative LLMs with various prompting strategies. The results reveal that current LLMs fall short of delivering satisfactory performance, with an overall score of merely 35.80%. Furthermore, through a detailed user study, we categorize the errors made by LLMs into ten problem-solving abilities. Our analysis indicates that no single prompting strategy significantly outperforms others and some strategies that demonstrate improvements in certain problem-solving skills result in declines in other skills. We envision that SciBench will catalyze further developments in the reasoning abilities of LLMs, thereby ultimately contributing to scientific research and discovery.</p>
</section>
<section id="challenging-chatgpt-with-chemistry-related-subjects" class="level1">
<h1>Challenging ChatGPT with Chemistry-Related Subjects</h1>
<p>Pimentel, et al <a href="https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2023-xl6w3" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2023-xl6w3</a> (unreviewed)</p>
<p>Abstract: Tools based on large language models such as ChatGPT may revolutionize information retrieval and knowledge discovery, particularly with the vast amount of electronic material available. In this communication we evaluate how two versions of ChatGPT can answer complex questions on chemistry-related subjects in six topics. The tools are still insufficient to deal with subtleties of complex topics, especially as they do not have access to the whole of the scientific literature. However, the progress from ChatGPT-3 to ChatGPT-4 is an indicator that we shall soon have tools to assist scientists in surveys, reviews of the literature, and for teaching.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-large-language-models-understand-chemistry-a-conversation-with-chatgpt" class="level1">
<h1>Do Large Language Models Understand Chemistry? A Conversation with ChatGPT</h1>
<p>Pimentel, et al,Journal of Chemical Information and Modeling 2023 63 (6), 1649-1655, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jcim.3c00285" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jcim.3c00285</a></p>
<p>Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have promised a revolution in answering complex questions using the ChatGPT model. Its application in chemistry is still in its infancy. This viewpoint addresses the question of how well ChatGPT understands chemistry by posing five simple tasks in different subareas of chemistry.</p>
</section>
<section id="generative-ai-in-education-and-research-opportunities-concerns-and-solutions" class="level1">
<h1>Generative AI in Education and Research: Opportunities, Concerns, and Solutions</h1>
<p>Alasadi &amp; Baiz, J. Chem. Educ. 2023, 100, 8, 2965–2971, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00323" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00323</a></p>
<p>Abstract: In this article, we discuss the role of generative artificial intelligence (AI) in education. The integration of AI in education has sparked a paradigm shift in teaching and learning, presenting both unparalleled opportunities and complex challenges. This paper explores critical aspects of implementing AI in education to advance educational goals, ethical considerations in scientific publications, and the attribution of credit for AI-driven discoveries. We also examine the implications of using AI-generated content in professional activities and describe equity and accessibility concerns. By weaving these key questions into a comprehensive discussion, this article aims to provide a balanced perspective on the responsible and effective use of these technologies in education, highlighting the need for a thoughtful, ethical, and inclusive approach to their integration.</p>
</section>
<section id="exploring-the-use-of-large-language-models-llms-in-chemical-engineering-education-building-core-course-problem-models-with-chat-gpt" class="level1">
<h1>Exploring the use of large language models (LLMs) in chemical engineering education: Building core course problem models with Chat-GPT</h1>
<p>Meng-Lin Tsai, et al, Education for Chemical Engineers, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ece.2023.05.001" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ece.2023.05.001</a></p>
<p>Abstract: This study highlights the potential benefits of integrating Large Language Models (LLMs) into chemical engineering education. In this study, Chat-GPT, a user-friendly LLM, is used as a problem-solving tool. Chemical engineering education has traditionally focused on fundamental knowledge in the classroom with limited opportunities for hands-on problem-solving. To address this issue, our study proposes an LLMs-assisted problem-solving procedure. This approach promotes critical thinking, enhances problem-solving abilities, and facilitates a deeper understanding of core subjects. Furthermore, incorporating programming into chemical engineering education prepares students with vital Industry 4.0 skills for contemporary industrial practices. During our experimental lecture, we introduced a simple example of building a model to calculate steam turbine cycle efficiency, and assigned projects to students for exploring the possible use of LLMs in solving various aspect of chemical engineering problems. Although it received mixed feedback from students, it was found to be an accessible and practical tool for improving problem-solving efficiency. Analyzing the student projects, we identified five common difficulties and misconceptions and provided helpful suggestions for overcoming them. Our course has limitations regarding using advanced tools and addressing complex problems. We further provide two additional examples to better demonstrate how to integrate LLMs into core courses. We emphasize the importance of universities, professors, and students actively embracing and utilizing LLMs as tools for chemical engineering education. Students must develop critical thinking skills and a thorough understanding of the principles behind LLMs, taking responsibility for their use and creations. This study provides valuable insights for enhancing chemical engineering education’s learning experience and outcomes by integrating LLMs.</p>
</section>
<section id="chatgpt-in-physics-education-a-pilot-study-on-easy-to-implement-activities" class="level1">
<h1>ChatGPT in physics education: A pilot study on easy-to-implement activities</h1>
<p>Bitzenbauer, Cont. Ed. Tech., 15, 3, <a href="https://doi.org/10.30935/cedtech/13176" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.30935/cedtech/13176</a></p>
<p>Abstract: Large language models, such as ChatGPT, have great potential to enhance learning and support teachers, but they must be used with care to tackle limitations and biases. This paper presents two easy-to-implement examples of how ChatGPT can be used in physics classrooms to foster critical thinking skills at the secondary school level. A pilot study (n=53) examining the implementation of these examples found that the intervention had a positive impact on students’ perceptions of ChatGPT, with an increase in agreement with statements related to its benefits and incorporation into their daily lives.</p>
</section>
<section id="assessment-of-chemistry-knowledge-in-large-language-models-that-generate-code" class="level1">
<h1>Assessment of chemistry knowledge in large language models that generate code</h1>
<p>White, et al, Digital Discovery, 2023,2, 368-376, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/D2DD00087C" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1039/D2DD00087C</a>, unreviewed preprint: <a href="https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2022-3md3n-v2" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2022-3md3n-v2</a></p>
<p>Abstract: In this work, we investigate the question: do code-generating large language models know chemistry? Our results indicate, mostly yes. To evaluate this, we introduce an expandable framework for evaluating chemistry knowledge in these models, through prompting models to solve chemistry problems posed as coding tasks. To do so, we produce a benchmark set of problems, and evaluate these models based on correctness of code by automated testing and evaluation by experts. We find that recent LLMs are able to write correct code across a variety of topics in chemistry and their accuracy can be increased by 30 percentage points via prompt engineering strategies, like putting copyright notices at the top of files. Our dataset and evaluation tools are open source which can be contributed to or built upon by future researchers, and will serve as a community resource for evaluating the performance of new models as they emerge. We also describe some good practices for employing LLMs in chemistry. The general success of these models demonstrates that their impact on chemistry teaching and research is poised to be enormous.</p>
</section>
<section id="natural-language-processing-models-that-automate-programming-will-transform-chemistry-research-and-teaching" class="level1">
<h1>Natural language processing models that automate programming will transform chemistry research and teaching</h1>
<p>Hocky and White, Digital Discovery, 2022, 1, 79-83, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/D1DD00009H" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1039/D1DD00009H</a></p>
<p>Abstract: Natural language processing models have emerged that can generate useable software and automate a number of programming tasks with high fidelity. These tools have yet to have an impact on the chemistry community. Yet, our initial testing demonstrates that this form of artificial intelligence is poised to transform chemistry and chemical engineering research. Here, we review developments that brought us to this point, examine applications in chemistry, and give our perspective on how this may fundamentally alter research and teaching.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-chatgpt-doingand-why-does-it-work" class="level1">
<h1>What is ChatGPT doing…and why does it work?</h1>
<p>Stephen Wolfram Writings: <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/" class="uri">https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/</a></p>
<p>YouTube video: <a href="https://youtu.be/flXrLGPY3SU?t=575" class="uri">https://youtu.be/flXrLGPY3SU?t=575</a></p>
<p><span hidden="">KEYWORDS: GPT, ChatGPT, LLM, teaching, chemistry </span></p>
</section>
<section id="future-trends-forum-discussing-the-future-of-education-and-technology" class="level1">
<h1>Future Trends Forum: Discussing the future of education and technology</h1>
<p>Bryan Alexander, <a href="http://forum.futureofeducation.us/about/">Future Trends Forum</a> YouTube video series on AI</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vrxNpMnVeFc">How can we teach creatively with AI?</a></p>
<p>Depauw University professor Harry Brown describes and shows his class experiments.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UDx0jksjVwM">How should academics react to AI?</a></p>
<p>How should higher education respond to new developments in artificial intelligence, such as ChatGPT and image creating applications?</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jCOQ-pWoMyY">How might Higher Education respond to AI?</a></p>
<p>Computer scientist and ed tech leader Ruben Puentedura explores the implications of large language model artificial intelligence.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=crBPM6DGQCQ&amp;list=PLlcx8yl6hlPC3QjlbIHzxGqCP3qRa0zcg&amp;index=2">Open Source AI for Higher Education</a></p>
<p>How can higher education grapple with artificial intelligence? We ask this question with a focus on an underdiscussed aspect: open source AI. Our guide is the excellent Forum favorite, computer scientist Ruben R. Puentedura, widely known as the creator of the SAMR framework for understanding the intersection of teaching and tech.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>article</category>
  <category>ai-ml</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/llms-gpt/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/llms-gpt/llm-gpt.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>3D Printing of Thermophysical Properties for Teaching Thermodynamics</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/3d-printing-thermophysical-properties/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/3d-printing-thermophysical-properties/3dthermo.webp" width="30%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>A central element of courses on thermodynamics at universities are the fundamentals of thermophysical property behavior. Thermophysical properties are often complex functions of at least two variables that comprise phase equilibria, metastable phases, critical points, etc. The thermal and caloric property behavior, e.g., <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p%20=%20p(v,%20T)"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?c_v%20=%20c_v(T,%20v)">, of pure substances and vapor–liquid phase equilibria of binary mixtures (pTx) are classical examples. A good spatial imagination is necessary for a complete understanding of the relations of the different properties and different phase regions. In this work, we explore how 3D printing can be used for visualizing thermophysical properties more vividly than classical 2D plots. This is tested using different thermodynamic property examples, e.g., the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p%20=%20p(v,%20T)"> surface of a pure substance with highlights for the binodal, spinodal, critical point, and characteristic isotherms. Also, three-dimensional objects describing fluid phase equilibria in binary mixtures are considered, e.g., azeotropic mixtures. The data for the 3D prints was obtained in this work from molecular-based equations of state. The 3D printed objects aim at providing the students vivid access to the relations and the behavior of thermophysical properties. We report on the first positive experiences using such 3D printed thermophysical properties in teaching.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Katharina Koehler, Johann Seibert, Gabriele Hornung, Simon Stephan, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.5c00277">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.5c00277</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>thermo</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/3d-printing-thermophysical-properties/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/3d-printing-thermophysical-properties/3dthermo.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Investigation of Simple and Complex Reaction Kinetics with a Simulated Program by LabVIEW</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/investigation-simple-complex-kinetics-labview/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/investigation-simple-complex-kinetics-labview/investigation.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>A chemical reaction kinetics simulation program was developed to simulate both simple and complex reactions with LabVIEW. In the case of simple reactions, the focus is on the kinetic characteristics of dual-reactant systems with different stoichiometric ratios at initial concentrations. For complex reactions, the characteristics of parallel, consecutive, reversible, and autocatalytic reactions are discussed. The numerical simulations from the program are close to the analytical solutions and can effectively reflect the kinetic characteristics of different types of reactions. The effectiveness of the simulation program in promoting learning was verified by experimental and control groups, and the score rate of the experimental group (89.7%) was significantly higher than that of the control group (66.6%). The results indicate that, with the help of the program, students can better construct the differential equations based on the law of mass action and understand the kinetic plots of different reactions as well as the relationship between the rates of the substance and the chemical reaction.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Li Liu, Qiang Fu, Qingsheng Gao, <em>J. Chem. Educ</em>., 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01332">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01332</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>kinetics</category>
  <category>computing</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/investigation-simple-complex-kinetics-labview/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/investigation-simple-complex-kinetics-labview/investigation.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Integrating Electronic Structure Theory Calculations with Python and Cheminformatics Tools</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/integrating-electronic-structure-python-cheminformatics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/integrating-electronic-structure-python-cheminformatics/est.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>The integration of electronic structure theory (EST) calculations with Python programming and cheminformatics tools presents a unique opportunity for enhancing chemistry education. This study shows how integrating Gaussian calculations with Python programming and libraries can be an effective approach for teaching computational chemistry. We present a comprehensive approach that bridges the gap between graphical user interface (GUI) interactions and programming in computational chemistry education. Our method introduces common calculations using Gaussian 16, demonstrating molecule generation, geometry optimization, and property prediction. We go beyond GUI interactions by providing complementary Python code that automates and expands these processes including scripts for generating Gaussian input files from various molecular representations. To enhance educational value, we incorporate implementations for generating molecular derivatives using RDKit and SURGE, enabling students to systematically explore structural variations. We demonstrate the integration of these tools in a practical example involving the analysis of explosive derivatives. This work also outlines several project ideas that utilize these integrated tools, providing a framework for educators to incorporate these methods into their chemistry curricula. Overall, we emphasize understanding the underlying principles of computer-based calculations and the importance of developing computational literacy through hands-on code development and customization in computational chemistry education. By integrating EST calculations with both commercial (Gaussian) and open-source (PySCF) packages, Python programming, and cheminformatics tools, this approach aims to develop students as not just software users but as computational chemists who understand the underlying principles and can adapt various EST platforms to tackle novel chemical challenges.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Dongseok Han, Hojin Han, Edward Chen, Walter J. Cesarski, Hyeongyun Lim, Hongseok Shin, Samuel V. Cowart, Enoch A. Nagelli, Simuck F. Yuk, Keunhong Jeong, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01171">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01171</a></p>
<p>Github repository: <a href="https://github.com/doas1min/Chem_Education">https://github.com/doas1min/Chem<sub>Education</sub></a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>computational</category>
  <category>computing</category>
  <category>jupyter</category>
  <category>python</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/integrating-electronic-structure-python-cheminformatics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/integrating-electronic-structure-python-cheminformatics/est.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why chemistry instructors are shifting to specifications grading: perceived benefits and challenges</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/why-chemistry-instructors-specifications-grading/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/why-chemistry-instructors-specifications-grading/specifications.png" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>Previous research extensively explored factors that are associated with instructors’ adoption of evidence-based instructional practices. However, an overlooked yet important aspect is exploring instructors’ motivation for implementing pedagogical innovations that are seemingly popular yet lack evidence of effectiveness. One such innovation that is gaining attention in postsecondary chemistry education is specifications grading, which aims to emphasize the learning process while mitigating some of the drawbacks of traditional grading. This study aims to provide insights into chemistry instructors’ decision to adopt specifications grading. In particular, we interviewed 29 chemistry instructors from 24 academic institutions in the United States who currently use this alternative grading scheme. The goal of these semi-structured interviews was to characterize these instructors’ perceptions of the advantages of specifications grading, their potential dissatisfaction with traditional grading, and potential challenges associated with implementing specifications grading in their courses. Our results indicate that instructors adopted specifications grading as a means to address their dissatisfaction with traditional grading. The commonly cited relative advantages of specifications grading include a perception that specifications grading increases student learning gains and provides greater flexibility for students. These findings provide insight into the dissemination strategy of innovation, highlighting a need for direct alignment between perceived advantages of pedagogical innovations to instructors’ dissatisfaction and instructors’ expressed real-world needs and aspirations for their classroom.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Wang, Ying and Machost, Haleigh and Yik, Brandon J. and Stains, Marilyne, <em>Chem. Educ. Res. Pract.</em>, 2025, <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/D5RP00035A">dx.doi.org/10.1039/D5RP00035A</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© Royal Society of Chemistry 2025</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>course design</category>
  <category>article</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/why-chemistry-instructors-specifications-grading/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/why-chemistry-instructors-specifications-grading/specifications.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="88" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Computer-Based Exercise on the Racemization Mechanism and Energy Barrier of Axially Chiral Molecules</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/computer-based-exercise-racemization/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/computer-based-exercise-racemization/racemization.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>Chirality is a fundamental property of nature, but it is challenging for undergraduate students to anticipate and understand the mechanism of racemization. In the density-functional-theory-based exercise described herein, students are introduced to tasks ranging from simple to complex to search transition states in the racemization process of a series of axially chiral biaryl molecules. The calculated racemization energy barriers range from 16.7 to 54.3 kcal/mol, mainly depending on the degree of steric hindrance between four ortho-position substituents. This visual and straightforward exercise is designed to stimulate students’ interest in organic and physical chemistry, provide insight into chemical mechanisms, and reveal the intrinsic relationships between structure and property.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Zijun Guan, Li−Li Liao, Yong-Yuan Gui, Cefei Zhang, Xiangge Zhou, Da-Gang Yu, Haifeng Xiang, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.5c00265">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.5c00265</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>computational</category>
  <category>activity</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/computer-based-exercise-racemization/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/computer-based-exercise-racemization/racemization.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Effects of Delaying Physical Laboratory Experiences on Student Self-Efficacy</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/effects-of-delaying-chemistry-lab/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/effects-of-delaying-chemistry-lab/delaying-lab.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>The COVID-19 pandemic was an unprecedented event that, out of necessity, drastically changed the way undergraduate chemistry courses were taught. With the cancellation of in-person classes, laboratory experiences were delayed and/or moved to the virtual space, the latter keeping the general framework of the laboratory experiment but removing the benchwork. In this program assessment, we used a set of timed surveys to assess the effects of delayed physical lab experiences and how an in-person inquiry-based laboratory project influences student self-efficacy in an undergraduate analytical chemistry class. Almost three-quarters of the students in this course had never had an in-person laboratory experience in college prior to this semester; many students shared feelings of anxiety and trepidation when approaching the laboratory experience in this intermediate-level chemistry course. In general, &gt;95% of students self-reported feeling higher confidence after completing the project lab experience. Overall, this program assessment brought to light the negative effects brought by delayed physical laboratory experiences in returning to in-person opportunities, especially postpandemic.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Amanda Rae Buchberger, Jericha Mill, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00772">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c00772</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>course design</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/effects-of-delaying-chemistry-lab/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/effects-of-delaying-chemistry-lab/delaying-lab.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Expanding the Horizons of UV–vis Spectroscopy Education: Beyond the Beer–Lambert Law</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/expanding-horizons-UV-vis-spectroscopy/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/expanding-horizons-UV-vis-spectroscopy/uv-vis.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>UV–visible (UV–vis) spectrophotometry is a fundamental analytical technique widely used in chemistry, biology, materials science, and medical research. Despite its significance, undergraduate education often presents UV–vis spectroscopy narrowly as an absorbance-based method governed by the Beer–Lambert Law. This traditional framework, while effective for idealized solutions, fails to address the complexities of real-world samples that scatter or emit light, leading to widespread challenges in data interpretation. To bridge this gap, this work introduces an expanded pedagogical approach that incorporates the theoretical foundations of UV–vis spectroscopy for solutions exhibiting diverse optical behaviors. These include pure absorbers, pure scatterers, simultaneous absorbers and scatterers, simultaneous absorbers and emitters, and solutions that encompass absorption, scattering, and emission. We present accessible theoretical models designed to accommodate students with varying levels of mathematical proficiency, parametrizing UV–vis signals within the capabilities of standard spectrophotometers. Additionally, we outline instructional strategies to enhance comprehension across different educational levels, making these advanced concepts more approachable. This framework lays the groundwork for future studies that will feature laboratory modules leveraging commercially available UV–vis and fluorescence spectrophotometers to reinforce hands-on, evidence-based learning. By broadening the scope of UV–vis education and addressing critical gaps in traditional instruction, this work aims to deepen students’ conceptual and practical understanding of spectroscopic analysis. Furthermore, it seeks to rectify common misinterpretations in the literature, equipping students with the analytical skills necessary for accurate, rigorous spectral interpretation. Ultimately, this effort aspires to transform UV–vis spectroscopy education by fostering both theoretical and practical mastery, preparing students for the challenges of modern scientific research and industry applications.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Pathum Wathudura, Huy Pham, Kumudu Siriwardana, Sumudu Athukorale, Udaya Jayasundara, Sameera R. Gunatilake, Zhong-Yan Cao, Willard E. Collier, Alena Moon, Dongmao Zhang*, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.5c00255">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.5c00255</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>spectroscopy</category>
  <category>article</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/expanding-horizons-UV-vis-spectroscopy/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/expanding-horizons-UV-vis-spectroscopy/uv-vis.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Comprehensive Learning on the Thermodynamic Description of Multicomponent Systems: A Guided Mind Mapping Approach</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/comprehensive-learning-thermodynamic-system-mindmap/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/comprehensive-learning-thermodynamic-system-mindmap/mindmap.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>The physical chemistry course encompasses a diverse range of abstract concepts, logical reasoning, mathematical formulations, and calculations. Many students in the field of chemistry approach this course with confusion. Mind mapping can provide a coherent knowledge framework that aids students in achieving a clearer understanding of the various dimensions of these concepts. This study aims to delineate the design and construction of mind maps to facilitate student comprehension regarding the thermodynamic description of multicomponent systems. Students’ responses to test exercises related to general formulas and their derivation of formulas served as primary data sources for analysis. The findings indicate that nearly all students successfully derived and applied thermodynamic formulas using guided mind mapping techniques. Furthermore, while mind mapping can help students engage with connections between chapters across different contexts, it may not sufficiently address the deeper understanding of individual concepts. Therefore, it is imperative for educators to elucidate the derivation process for key formulas by demonstrating “how this is accomplished”. By emphasizing interconnections between chapters, encouraging practice with newly acquired concepts alongside previously mastered knowledge, and fostering repeated reflection through practice, students can progressively attain a more integrated state of understanding. Ultimately, it is concluded that the guided mind mapping approach can effectively support comprehensive learning among students regarding the thermodynamic description of multicomponent systems.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Le Luo, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01382">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01382</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>thermo</category>
  <category>article</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/comprehensive-learning-thermodynamic-system-mindmap/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/comprehensive-learning-thermodynamic-system-mindmap/mindmap.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Pedagogical Tour of the Fourier Transform with Applications to NMR and IR Spectroscopy</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/a-pedagogical-tour-ft-nmr/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/a-pedagogical-tour-ft-nmr/tour.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>The Fourier Transform (FT) is a fundamental tool that permeates modern science and technology. While chemistry undergraduates encounter the FT as early as the second year, their courses often only mention it in passing because computers frequently perform it automatically behind the scenes. Although this automation enables students to focus on ‘the chemistry’, students miss out on an opportunity to understand and use one of the most powerful tools in the scientific arsenal capable of revealing how time-dependent signals encode chemical structure. Although many educational resources introduce chemists to the FT, they often require familiarity with sophisticated mathematical and computational concepts. Here, we present a series of three self-contained, Python-based laboratory activities designed for undergraduates to understand the FT and apply it to analyze audio signals, an infrared (IR) spectroscopy interferogram, and a nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) free induction decay (FID). In these activities, students observe how the FT reveals and quantifies the contribution of each frequency present in a temporal signal and how decay time scales dictate signal broadening. Our activities empower students with the tools to transform their own temporal data sets (e.g., FID) to a frequency spectrum. To ensure accessibility of the activities and lower the barrier to implementation, we utilize Google Colab’s open-source, cloud-based platform to run Jupyter notebooks. We also offer a prelaboratory activity that introduces students to the basics of Python and the Colab platform and reviews the math and programming skills needed to complete the lab activities. These lab activities help students build a qualitative, quantitative, and practical understanding of the FT.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Anthony J. Dominic III, Nicholas L. Cipolla, William C. Pfalzgraff, Jeffrey A. Jankowski, Rebecca J. Rapf, Andrés Montoya-Castillo, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01439">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01439</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>nmr</category>
  <category>spectroscopy</category>
  <category>computing</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/a-pedagogical-tour-ft-nmr/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/a-pedagogical-tour-ft-nmr/tour.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A review of research on the teaching and learning of quantum mechanics</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/a-review-teaching-learning-quantum-mechanics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/a-review-teaching-learning-quantum-mechanics/review.png" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>In this work, we review research on the teaching and learning of quantum mechanics in chemistry courses. This systematic review builds on previous reviews in chemistry education research that focused on the other highly quantitative, calculation-heavy topics covered in upper-level physical chemistry courses (kinetics and thermodynamics). We aim to provide a resource for both practitioners and education researchers. Based on the topics of the research conducted in our sample (N=50), we grouped the articles into six categories: (1) students’ general challenges with quantum mechanics; (2) students’ conceptions of the atom; (3) students’ conceptions of bonding; (4) students’ conceptions of the quantum nature of light; (5) students’ conceptions of commonly used quantum mechanical models; (6) curricular materials and instruction. Relevant trends stemming from this work include that much of the research leans on education research in mathematics and physics to support the claim that students have difficulties with mathematics; however, these claims require further investigation within chemistry education contexts. Moreover, a suprising amount of research on quantum mechanics involved students sampled outside of upper-level chemistry courses (i.e., secondary-level and general chemistry contexts).</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>S. C. McAfee, F. M. Watts and J. G. Rodriguez, Chem. Educ. Res. Pract., 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/D5RP00030K">DOI: /10.1039/D5RP00030K</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©The Royal Society of Chemistry 2025</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>article</category>
  <category>course design</category>
  <category>quantum</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/a-review-teaching-learning-quantum-mechanics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/a-review-teaching-learning-quantum-mechanics/review.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="82" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Interactive Application and Visualization of the Variational Method to Aid Conceptual Understanding of Introductory Quantum Mechanics</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/interactive-application-variational-method/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/interactive-application-variational-method/variational.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>We introduce a self-guided, interactive JupyterLab to familiarize undergraduate students with introductory quantum mechanics concepts. In the lab, the linear variational method is applied to a confined particle that is subject to various 1-dimensional potentials, including a step potential, a central potential, a double barrier potential, and parabolic and intersecting parabola potentials. Through visualization of multiple scenarios, students learn about parity and its consequences, tunneling and delocalization, the size and quality of the basis set, and the effect of boundaries and potential surface curvature on ground state probabilities. Chemical applications include ammonia inversion, light absorption by cyanine dyes, and vibrational transitions in HCl. The lab is geared toward students with limited exposure to quantum mechanics and no coding or “pen-and-paper” math is required. All code is hidden and student interaction is through buttons, sliders and fillable fields.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Arjan van der Vaart, Sang T. Le Phan, Brielle Wolfe, J. Chem. Educ., 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01560">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01560</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>quantum</category>
  <category>jupyter</category>
  <category>python</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/interactive-application-variational-method/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/interactive-application-variational-method/variational.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Open-Source DFT Calculations of Electronic Structure to Understand Bonding in Solids</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/open-source-dft-bonding-solids/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/open-source-dft-bonding-solids/open-source-dft.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>Computational materials chemistry is an ever-evolving interdisciplinary field where advancements in research capabilities require equally innovative pedagogy that combines learning, content distribution, and access. One area that bridges classroom and laboratory settings with practical hands-on learning is the use of open-source density functional theory (DFT) calculations of electronic band structures. Here, we describe to a general audience the methodology, workflow, and tutorials we have developed over five years to train student researchers. Specifically, these tutorials are for semiconductors and oxides introduced in beginner level courses which are then discussed again at various points later on in the chemistry curriculum. We provide a general overview of the background necessary to combine solid-state chemistry and electronic structure methods for instructors and DFT beginners. The remainder of the tutorial emphasizes structure–property relationships to enhance conceptual learning and make connections across the chemistry curriculum. Complete workflows for computing the electronic structure of semiconductor solids common to undergraduate and graduate chemistry curricula are presented, along with new resources for teaching computational materials chemistry. This tutorial provides multiple sets of input files and a step-by-step visualization guide to calculate band structures and projected density of states (PDOS), along with detailed descriptions that can be used to guide classroom discussions and enhance computational skills. This interdisciplinary tutorial aims to lower the barrier to entry for teachers, students, and researchers new to the field by outlining both the workflow, use, outcomes and assessments possible with freely available resources.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Mona Layegh, Joseph W. Bennett, J. Chem. Educ., 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01442">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01442</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>computational</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/open-source-dft-bonding-solids/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/open-source-dft-bonding-solids/open-source-dft.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pedagogical Revision of Spontaneous Emission and Photons</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/pedagogical-revision-spontaneous-emission/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/pedagogical-revision-spontaneous-emission/spontaneous.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>This article provides teaching material on classical and quantum electromagnetic field theory for undergraduate and graduate chemistry students. It focuses on the concepts of spontaneous emission and the photon as explained by quantum electromagnetic field theory. In general chemistry classrooms, these concepts are introduced early on using the well-known Jablonski diagram. However, we argue that the current approach to teaching spontaneous emission and the photon in chemistry needs to be re-evaluated in light of insights from quantum electromagnetic field theory. This article presents a revised proposal for teaching these topics.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Atanu Bhattacharya, Elliot R. Bernstein, Gurazada Ravi Kumar, Arpan Chakraborty, Jayatirtha Mangalvedekar, Jayanta Ghosh, Moulinath Roy, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01030">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01030</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>article</category>
  <category>quantum</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/pedagogical-revision-spontaneous-emission/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/pedagogical-revision-spontaneous-emission/spontaneous.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Review of Undergraduate Chemistry Teaching in Higher Education during 2019–2023</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/review-undergraduate-chemistry-teaching-2019-2023/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/review-undergraduate-chemistry-teaching-2019-2023/review.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>This review examines the evolution of tertiary undergraduate chemistry teaching from 2019 to 2023, including in response to the global pandemic’s impact on teaching and learning methods and whether those adaptations have persisted. The authors assessed the current educational landscape against standards set by leading accreditation bodies, the American Chemical Society, the Royal Society of Chemistry, and the Royal Australian Chemical Institute. A systematic research method allowed comprehensive coverage of peer reviewed literature using two databases: Web of Science and SciFinder. A total of 511 papers were included in this review, and 245 highly cited articles were classified into five themes: students as learners, curriculum, instructional material, educational innovation, and context. Using these themes, it was possible to find the major implications of research in tertiary chemistry teaching within the literature for the five-year period. Key findings show that experiential learning through in-person laboratory activities is affirmed. Virtual resources developed during the pandemic, however, were mostly moved post pandemic to prelaboratory or complementary activities. Integration of innovative technologies and games into teaching can improve student engagement and learning, but also presents opportunities, such as generative artificial intelligence for the development of student critical thinking skills and communication skills. Students valued learning with authentic examples or big-picture contexts, like climate change or systems thinking. An emergent theme was improvements in inclusive chemistry education. This embracing of technology alongside traditional methods, and the rise of interdisciplinary approaches and inclusivity, equips graduates with the skills necessary for successful careers in chemistry.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Wendy A. Loughlin, Sarah L. Cresswell, J. Chem., Educ., 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01435">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01435</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>article</category>
  <category>course design</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/review-undergraduate-chemistry-teaching-2019-2023/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/review-undergraduate-chemistry-teaching-2019-2023/review.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Thermal Effects in Optically Detected Magnetic Resonance of Nitrogen Vacancies in Diamond: A Quantum Thermometer for a Graduate Teaching Lab</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/thermal-effect-optically-detected-vacancies/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/thermal-effect-optically-detected-vacancies/thermal.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>This work reports a study of thermal effects in nitrogen vacancies in diamond using the optically detected continuous wave magnetic resonance (cw-ODMR) method. Changes in the ODMR signal induced by heating the diamond sample with both laser light at various powers and by a simple heater were investigated and analyzed. The influence of heating on the ODMR signal was measured for two types of synthetic diamond powder─a low cost microcrystalline powder (particle diameters ca. 80 μm) and a high purity nanodiamond powder (particle diameters ca. 140 nm). The experimental setup can be viewed as a pedagogical quantum thermometer. A number of cost-effective components were used, e.g., a self-constructed confocal microscope, and the Raspberry Pi 4B microcomputer in an experiment control and data acquisition system, as well as an inexpensive microwave modulator, analog to digital converter, and a heating plate.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Gustaw Szawioła, Szymon Mieloch, Danuta Stefańska Przemysław Głowacki, Agata Frajtak, Jędrzej Michalczyk, Krzysztof Murawski, Andrzej Pruchlat, Jan Raczyński, Michał Schmidt, Jerzy Sobkowski, Maksymilian Wosicki, Andrzej Biadasz, Adam Buczek, Anna Dychalska, Piotr Mazerewicz, Mirosław Szybowicz, J. Chem. Educ., 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01434">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01434</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>lab</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/thermal-effect-optically-detected-vacancies/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/thermal-effect-optically-detected-vacancies/thermal.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Visualizing Ruby Emission Decay Lifetime with Slow-Motion Digital Cameras: A Demonstration for Students</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/visualizing-ruby-emission-decay-lifetime/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/visualizing-ruby-emission-decay-lifetime/ruby.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>This short article describes a safe way of observing the emission decay from a ruby crystal using a photographic flash. This demonstration does not require the use of lasers and can be easily and safely performed in a classroom or a home setting. The ruby sample was optically excited with a short-duration photographic flash, and the subsequent relaxation of the excited state population through intermediate metastable states was monitored using three different types of slow-motion digital cameras. Monitoring the recorded video frames allowed visualization of the population decay kinetics. In addition, the measurement of frame intensities allowed for the computation of the excited state lifetime and decay rate constant. This demonstration can be utilized in several different chemical education courses at the advanced high school or undergraduate level, for example, in the courses that involve concepts related to photochemical reaction kinetics, flash photolysis, lasers, etc.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Dinesh Dhankhar, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01529">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01529</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>©2025 American Chemical Society and Division of Chemical Education, Inc.</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>lab</category>
  <category>kinetics</category>
  <category>spectroscopy</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/visualizing-ruby-emission-decay-lifetime/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/visualizing-ruby-emission-decay-lifetime/ruby.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Teaching chemists to code with diversity in mind: a pedagogy of belonging for end-user conditions</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/teaching-chemists-code-with-diversity/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/teaching-chemists-code-with-diversity/formation.png" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p>While teaching students to code is a valuable skill, we need to consider the equity implications of such instruction. Computer programming is a highly stereotyped activity, and as such can negatively impact a student’s sense of chemistry identity. This is likely to be especially acute for students from historically excluded groups. Recommendations for coding instruction that will support a student’s sense of chemistry identity are given. These include pedagogies that encourage student interaction (Live Coding, spending class time for introductory instruction), differentiating by prior knowledge, and knowing how computer scientists talk about coding. By using pedagogies that increase student’s chemistry identity during programming instruction, we can send the message that all students belong in our field.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>van Staveren M., ChemRxiv. 2025; <a href="https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-sbhws">doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-sbhws</a> This content is a preprint and has not been peer-reviewed.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0</a></div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>article</category>
  <category>course design</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/teaching-chemists-code-with-diversity/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/teaching-chemists-code-with-diversity/formation.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="95" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using Prequestioning as a Hands-On Activity to Support Undergraduate Student Learning</title>
  <link>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/using-prequestioning-activity/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/using-prequestioning-activity/prequestioning.webp" width="40%" align="right" style="padding: 10px 0px 0px 10px;"></p>
<p><em>Prequestioning</em> is a learning strategy that involves taking practice tests on to-be-learned information, followed by studying the correct answers. Despite promising results in laboratory studies, it has rarely been examined in authentic educational settings. In this activity, we implemented prequestioning as an interactive, hands-on activity in a small undergraduate environmental chemistry course. Across 10 lecture sessions, the instructor administered four prequestions targeting concepts to be covered in the upcoming lecture. Students attempted to guess the answers to each question before the lecturer presented the correct answers. On assessments occurring during the next lecture session, there was evidence of a prequestioning effect, that is, better performance on questions targeting prequestioned concepts versus non-prequestioned concepts, in most cases. The observed benefit of prequestioning highlights the potential utility of this strategy as a useful and affordable activity for enhancing learning in undergraduate chemistry and other similar courses.</p>
<section id="reference" class="level1">
<h1>Reference</h1>
<p>Steven C. Pan, Jia Yi Han, Fun Man Fung, <em>J. Chem. Educ.</em>, 2025, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01405">doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.4c01405</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>article</category>
  <category>course design</category>
  <guid>https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/using-prequestioning-activity/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chemistry.coe.edu/piper/posts/using-prequestioning-activity/prequestioning.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
